good morning on behalf
of federation of india's community
associations
fica and especially
on behalf of asian indian american
physicians of northeast ohio apno it
gives me
great pleasure to congratulate
the the recent and the newest inductee
into the cleveland international hall of
fame mr ramesha
mahatma gandhi said in order to find
yourself
lose in the service of others and
rameshbhai
has done exactly that by taking medical
service
to remote parts of india where the
health infrastructure didn't exist
an effort he called medical yatra or
medical pilgrimage
is a signal contribution to both
indian and american diaspora's
reputation
and the great work he has done i want to
also mention that ramesh bhai
is unique in that he is part of the very
first
husband-wife team to be inducted into
the international hall of fame
so ramesh bhai and jayawin both are
inductees and we are extremely proud of
that
so ramesh my felicitations on behalf of
fica hypno and the entire indian
community
and it gives me great pleasure to give
you
this award
this award that commemorates your
induction into the cleveland
international hall of fame
thank you congratulations
ramesh you and i
have been here for a long time
and on top of that you and i were both
working in wickliffe many many years and
we didn't meet
[Applause]
it was only after that
that we got involved in the uh
community activity then we would connect
that
that we got connected
and of course what is very very
prominent
in india and indian culture is the word
seva and that
is something that
ramesh and jai have done
worldwide in taking care of
the health of people that
maybe are not in a position
to afford to pay for their healthcare
and it is so nice
that we have taken the time
to recognize you and your better have
on this occasion i can only say
this is the only city in my research
that has something like the cultural
gardens
which represent
a worldwide community
and their efforts
in making cleveland great there is no
other place
in the united states that i know
that can match the
cleveland cultural garden so keep up the
good work
this is the only place in my research
that has mahatma gandhi
statue in the cultural gardens
on a martin luther king drive
martin luther king was so impressed by
mahatma gandhi
that he went out of his way to make
sure and start something
in the united states
so here you are sir
the recognition
i'm not sure
[Applause]
oh
and those recognized
for their seva in making sure
that you make a big difference in the
world
and i know you and jaya do
because you have traveled all over
to make sure that people
who are unable to afford
health issues
that they are there with your presence
and health exam
to make a difference thank you
my husband is a unique person
i being a doctor i decided that i want
to do
medical work wherever is needed and
first
first repose in mexico with some other
group and i said i'm going to go
he says i'm coming but what you're going
to do
i'm going to do the medical no i'm
coming
so he came with us i was the only doctor
in the group so i do the medical work
and he was working with the other people
bathing the poor mexican kids cutting
their hair putting them in the fresh
clothes and all
and they self-distracted and from then
on we have
gone to so many different countries
wherever i went he came like
ecuador uganda kenya
haiti honduras and then we started our
own medical yatra with ethno
association of indian physicist of
northern ohio
when we hit the tsunami and that time we
started our
own and he was the executive director
for the medical yatra of hypno
and we have done about 20 trips to india
every year we go
and that was the main thing we did
together but he has done so much other
voluntary work like
his teaching with junior achievement is
several schools and
working with you he
and so many like working in the soup
kitchens distributing food to the poor
people stuff like that
but he's all the life he just wants to
do things for the people
dad we're very proud of you for
receiving this
award recognizing your years of service
both in cleveland as well as across the
world
you've been a model for serving others
whether that's our community here in
cleveland both the indian community
as well as the broader community as well
as serving both
the indian diaspora worldwide
as well as many others i've admired how
you've approached
all of your tasks with initiative with
entrepreneurship
and most importantly positive enthusiasm
that encourages others to participate
with you
so congratulations on this well-deserved
honor
my dear friends of global
community of greater cleveland
thank you kindly to make many
an instrument of accepting this
prestigious award and
honor but i truly believe
from the best corner of my heart there
are so many
individuals and organizations
contributed to make this owner
possible it's very difficult
if not impossible to name all of them
but let me share a few of them with you
these are my life lessons
[Applause]
at tender age of seven i lost
both of my parents father and then
mother
my life was completely dark
full of anxieties and fear
no clue for next day
next month or future
two of my older brothers kanti
and gulab with their newly married
wives lifted me up
cuddled me loved me unconditionally
and put me through school and college
education
i am deeply grateful for them to see
this event
happening today that was my first lesson
of life
life's strongest foundation is love
family values and sacrifices
on august 21 1966
somebody else entered my life dr jayasah
as my wife putting more fertilizers
and water to strengthen the family
foundation my son baiju
and my daughter bella with my grandkids
they are other building blocks i'm
extremely grateful for their love and
care
to save my life
number two i'm born in a small village
of borderline near city of surah
my dream in my school just was to visit
shulat city 20 mice
through my hometown to see the movies
in the theater and explain joy of city
life
i experienced death at the age of 17
when i took exam of the 12th grade
then i went to mumbai for engineering
college of education
during the last year of engineering in
i got the bug that i wanted to go to
united states for
higher education i want to go to united
states for higher education
that was my dream my dream
to come to united states but my brothers
told me
we don't have money i cannot buy your
tickets
to go to united states forget about the
expenses
of lodging and boarding by god's grace
one of the trusts from mumbai gave me a
loan
to buy my ticket to come to united
states to make my dream
come true i learned second
lesson of my life dream
dream big dream more
work hard your plans and angel is
waiting
for you somewhere
united states education of masters in
double e
and mba provided me an
enormous opportunity to improve our
standard of living
and provide ivy league education to my
son
and my daughter i'm extremely grateful
to divine to make my dreams
come true
number three in 1991
my wife decided to start studying our
tenants
scale and fortune of good luck
with under south persons
around the world norman bitler
president of buses international from
laurent ohio
invited us to join with the humanitarian
mission
in loreto mexico
they are being a physician provided free
examination
and medicine to hundreds of poor mexican
children
but i do not have any medical skills no
what do i do romance a lot of children
are dirty
as you can see they do not have running
water
here can you give them a bath
yes i will do that no
then well here is a pair of scissors
cut their hair and make them million
dollar kits
norm i will do that in voluntary week
work for seva work adaptivity
and humility are very valuable traits
in hindi culture we call it seva
just do god's work without asking a
question
without expecting any rewards
i learned the third lesson life is an
opportunity benefit from it
give give more give
to give that's the message of shiva
number four in 2009
my wife jaya and i were invited to a
cleveland rotary meeting
at windows on the river michael jones
first international vice president of
the rotary
was the speaker and mike shared with the
audience
his experience working in nigeria
country highly underdeveloped in
medicine and human health
rotary international has been giving a
credible
amount of financial health through
rotary projects
to uplift the poor population of nigeria
after the meeting i asked mike
can i do so for india if i joined rotary
my country president both of them said
yes
i sign up to become a rotary member
in last 10 years totally international
number of rotary clubs in india and usa
and associated indian physicians
have helped me to invest
more than 1.2
million dollars in sustainable projects
we have done free surgeries we have
provided mobile vent clinics
we have done the dialysis centers we had
an operation theater
we have water treatment plants rotary
has helped me
to have hundreds of poor villagers free
surgery
pre-cancer treatment pre-cataract
that one thousand dollars of membership
of rotary paid up enormous
and benefits to my countrymen
i learned the lesson number four life is
continually learning and growing
learning and growing with my wife i had
a good fortune to visit
mexico honduras haiti
dominican republic uganda kenya ecuador
[Applause]
with adaptability and humility
i enjoyed every one of them
spiritually i feel more connected
to all of the souls of different culture
different races different colors
in hindu culture we call it
vasudeva kottumbakam
the whole world is a family
i learned the fifth light of compassion
caring and loving to everybody
was to take
i returned to india in 1965
for good to dedicate my talents and
energy
to india's benefit i
invested hundred percent of my life
savings
in the enterprise in 1966
in india but a couple of fox
cheated me and manipulated to file me
from that enterprise
and then i had to fight back legally in
indian court which took 10 years
in the meantime my bank account
was bottomed out i was literally
on the street now i have to rebuild
i was bleeding inside i was
angry i could not sleep i could not
forget
what those sark people did it to me
how much disruption that did it to jaya
and me
we were wiped out i returned back to
united states
in 1969 after four years in india
to rebuild my life here
from 1979 to 1990 i
hated india i crossed india
because of my open bones i was
hemorrhaging
inside i do not want to go back to india
all people in india are corrupt and
sucks
i talked then i met a spiritual leader
master who spent a lot of time
counseling he said
ramez what happened to you
in 66 67 was not fair
was not good yes i agree with you
but those were only 10 and the private
and people
who harmed you what about the rest of
the millions of people
who loved you they provide you college
education
who help you to be here
can you forget their obligation you must
go back to your country
touch that sacred soil again and get the
first
nourishment since 2001
i've been broke india every year
the last 20 years
to get past fresh perspective from my
motherland
india i love my country and all the good
things happen to me
in medical aftermath and even two days
even
is because i heal myself
from those wounds i think gratefully
to those 10 person
who made me come back to united states
to restart
and helping make a human against
humongous contribution to rotary to my
motherland
india i forgave them forever
lesson number six i learned life
is a mystery life is two places
do not destroy it if it is a lemon
make a lemonade out of it organics can
heal
a lot of wounds let me share with you
loudly with more emphasis this
award belongs to all rotary clubs
and rotary international and associated
opinion position of the open world all
christian
and volunteers were supported jayaz and
maya fort
on medical mission all networking
partners in india
and the united states and all
institutions
who educated me my friends and my family
i'm very happy to accept this event
on their behalf very very
grateful